<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>King William's toleration being an explanation of that liberty of religion, which may be expected from His Majesty's declaration, with a bill for comprehension &amp; indulgence, drawn up in order to an act of Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12304534</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12304534</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59203</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59203)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 637:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>King William's toleration being an explanation of that liberty of religion, which may be expected from His Majesty's declaration, with a bill for comprehension &amp; indulgence, drawn up in order to an act of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
                  <author>Nottingham, Heneage Finch, Earl of, 1621-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Hayhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Toleration act was drafted by Lord Nottingham.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Toleration.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59203:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>King William's TOLERATION: BEING AN EXPLANATION OF THAT <hi>Liberty of Religion,</hi> Which may be Expected from His Majeſty's Declaration.</p>
            <p>WITH A BILL FOR Comprehenſion &amp; Indulgence, Drawn up in Order to an <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LICENSED, <hi>March</hi> the 25. 1689, <hi>Iames Fraſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Hayhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Axe,</hi> in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> 1689,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59203:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59203:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Toleration Explain'd.</head>
            <p>SINCE it hath pleaſed his preſent Gracious Majeſty, <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> the Third, in his Declaration, upon his Coming into the Kingdom, to ſignifie, That <hi>this Expedition was intended for no other deſign, but to have a free Parliament,</hi> and to have <hi>That</hi> (as more eſpecially expreſſing his mind) <hi>for the making ſuch Laws, as may Eſtabliſh a good Agreement between the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and all Proteſtant Diſſenters; as alſo for the Covering of all ſuch, who will live peaceably under the Government, as becomes good Subjects, from all Perſecution upon the account of their Religion:</hi> I cannot but think it a very ſeaſonable and acceptable piece of Service, to make ſome little larger Explanation upon theſe Words; which carry in them the full Purport of theſe two things, which we call <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> and <hi>Indulgence;</hi> and which no Wiſe man but will ſee (if they be drawn up into ſuch a Bill, as they ought, and paſs the Houſes) are the true means to the Settlement, and Happineſs of the Nation.</p>
            <p>I ſhall preſent the Explanation; Then offer ſuch a Bill; And make ſome Animadverſion on it; and that is the Buſineſs of this Paper.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, in this Atchievement then, or Deſign (full of all Princely Wiſdom, Honeſty, and Goodneſs) there is a Double inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to be diſtinguiſhed, and weighed; That of <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf, and that of the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Advance of Religion does conſiſt much in the Unity of its Profeſſors, both in Opinion and Practice; to be of one Mind, and one Heart, and one Way (in Diſcipline and Worſhip) ſo far as may be according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The Advance of the <hi>Nation</hi> does lie in the Freedom and Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Trade,</hi> and ingrafting the whole Body into the Common Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and Dependance on the Government.</p>
            <p>The <hi>One</hi> of theſe calls for an <hi>Eſtabliſhed Order</hi> and <hi>Agreement:</hi> the <hi>Other</hi> beſpeaks an <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and the fulleſt <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> that is but <hi>Tolerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For while People are in danger of ſuffering about <hi>Religion,</hi> they dare
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59203:3"/>
not launch into <hi>Trade,</hi> but keep their <hi>Money,</hi> as knowing not into what Streights they may be driven: and when, in reference to their <hi>Sect</hi> and <hi>Party,</hi> they are held under <hi>Severity,</hi> it is eaſie for thoſe who are deſigning Heads, to Mould them into Wrath and Faction; which, without that occaſion, would melt and diſſolve it ſelf into bare diſſent of <hi>Opinion,</hi> peaceably rejoycing under the Enjoyment of an equal <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King is concern'd as <hi>Supreme</hi> Governour, and as <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour. As he is King, he is to ſeek the Welfare of the Nation; as he is <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> the Flouriſhing of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion is particularly his intereſt, not only as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked with <hi>Holland,</hi> and his <hi>Allies;</hi> but as this Kingdom does lye in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance ſtill with its Neighbour Nations.</p>
            <p>The Judgment now of ſome hath been for a <hi>Comprehending</hi> Act, which might take in thoſe that are for our Parochial Churches, that the Laws then might be more ſeverely Executed upon all thoſe that ſeparate from Them, in order to their Reduction: But the Judgment of ſome others is for a Free and Equal Act of Crace to all indifferently, whether Separatiſts or Others, abhorring <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> as more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to them upon that account mentioned, than all the Acts that have paſſed.</p>
            <p>Neither of theſe judge up to the full intereſt of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as is propoſed. It becomes not him, whoſe Principles will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to own our <hi>Parochial Churches,</hi> and enjoy a Living, to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have his Brethren, that cannot, to be given up to Perſecution. And it becomes not the <hi>Separatiſt,</hi> if he may not enjoy his Conſcience, to repine and envy another for reaping any farther Emolument, ſeeing both of them (ſuppoſing the latter may do ſo) will have as much at the Bottom, as can be in their Capacities deſired of either.</p>
            <p>It is an Act therefore of a Mixt Complection, providing both <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion</hi> and <hi>Indulgence,</hi> for the different Parties, that muſt ſerve the Nation.</p>
            <p>There are Two forts of the Proteſtant Diſſenters. One that owns the Eſtabliſhed Miniſtry, and our Pariſh Congregations, and are in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of Union upon that account, deſiring it heartily upon ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations only, as may but ſatisfie their Conſciences in the Matter: The Other that owns not our Churches, and ſo are uncapable of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction,</hi> who do not, and cannot deſire, or ſeek it.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>One,</hi> that which is to be propoſed, is a farther Latitude in the preſent <hi>Conſtituted Order,</hi> that ſuch may be received; and this we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59203:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
call <hi>Comprehenſion.</hi> For the <hi>Other,</hi> there is indeed nothing can be done to bring thoſe in, and joyn them with us in Parochial Union; yet is there this to be propounded, That we bear with them, and not let any one that lives peaceably be Perſecuted for his Conſcience; and this we call <hi>Indulgence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> now may be <hi>Comprehended,</hi> he will be ſatisfied to act in his Miniſtry, without any endeavouring the alteration of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> any otherwiſe than as conducive to advance that <hi>Comprehenſion.</hi> If the <hi>Congregationaliſt</hi> be <hi>Indulged,</hi> he will be ſatisfied, though he be not <hi>Comprehended;</hi> for That he cannot come up to: And ſo ſhall there be no Diſobligation put on any but all be pleaſed, and enjoy the Benefit of ſuch a Bill.</p>
            <p>Let but the Stakes for Comprehenſion be ſet wide enough, to take in all who can own, and come into the Publick Liturgy, (which are far the greater Weight of the Nation) and when the Countenance of Authority, and all State-Emoluments are caſt into one Scale; and nothing but <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> put in the other, the Men that <hi>Conform</hi> not, being let alone to come to themſelves, without <hi>Perſecution</hi> to <hi>enflame</hi> them, or <hi>Preferment</hi> to <hi>encourage</hi> them, (eſpecially if one Expedient be uſed, that is, ſome other Bill be preferred againſt Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities, to let in the <hi>Comprehended</hi> to ſomething, that ſuch as come in may find it really better to them, to be a <hi>Prieſt</hi> to a <hi>Tribe,</hi> than a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite</hi> to a <hi>Family,)</hi> we need not doubt, but Time, the Miſtriſs of the Wiſe and the Unwiſe, will diſcover the peaceable Fruit of ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the <hi>Deſign</hi> and <hi>Explanation</hi> of it. Now for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing, A <hi>Bill</hi> to comprize the Contents, and to prevent all <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant</hi> and <hi>inſufficient</hi> Endeavours of any <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Party,</hi> to <hi>ſhorten,</hi> or <hi>widen</hi> that Liberty of Religion, more than is meet, or charitable to their Brethren, on one ſide or the other, which we may expect from our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> and preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the accompliſhment of His Majeſties Royal <hi>Words,</hi> ſo well tempered with Benignity and Wiſdom, in his <hi>Declaration</hi> at firſt mentioned, and unto which the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may undoubtedly truſt: I ſhall need nothing, but to Re-print a Bill, which any one may find who pleaſe, (that no Body may take Exceptions thereupon) in a certain bound Book, call'd, <hi>The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan,</hi> ſet forth in the Year, 1682. being the reſult of much Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Houſe of Commons, for Eaſe and Mitigation to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters ſo long ago, and put together by conſent of ſuch that knew beſt their own Grievances in this manner, to lie by, and ſerve ſuch an Occaſion.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="bill">
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59203:4"/>
                        <head>The Bill for <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> and <hi>Indulgence.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHEREAS The Peace of the State is highly concern'd in the Peace of the Church; therefore, at all Times, but eſpecially in this Conjuncture, it is moſt Neceſſary to be preſerved. In Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therefore to remove Differences, and Diſſatisfactions, which may ariſe among Proteſtants:</hi> BE IT ENACTED, <hi>by the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, by, and with the Advice and Conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this preſent Parliament Aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame,</hi> THAT <hi>if any Perſon ſhall (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any Interpretation of his own, unleſs it be ſuch as ſhall be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Dioceſan, which if it be Orthodox he ſhall do) Subſcribe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Aſſent, and Conſent unto, and Approbation of the Articles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, mention'd in the Statute made in the</hi> 13th. <hi>Year of the Late Queen</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth; <hi>except only, the</hi> 34th. 35th. <hi>and</hi> 36th. <hi>Articles; and alſo, except theſe Words in the</hi> 20th. <hi>Article,</hi> viz. The Church hath Power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree Rites and Ceremonies, and Authority in Controverſies of Faith; <hi>in like manner, as he is already obliged to Subſcribe and Declare his Aſſent and Conſent unto, and Approbation of all the ſaid</hi> 39. <hi>Articles: Every ſuch Perſon ſhall be as capable of Taking any Degree, in either Univerſity, or being ordained Prieſt or Deacon, or of being collated, admitted, or put into, and to hold and enjoy any Eccleſiaſtical Benefice, or Promotion, as if the ſaid Perſon had Subſcribed and Declared his Aſſent and Conſent unto, and Approbation of all the ſaid Articles of Religion.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AND <hi>be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforeſaid, That every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Ordained, between the Year of our Lord,</hi> 1644. <hi>and the Firſt of</hi> May, <hi>in the Year,</hi> 1660. <hi>according to the Form of Ordination, uſed by laying on of Hands by the Presbytery, ſhall be as capable of any Eccleſiaſtical Benefice or Promotion, as if he had been Ordained, according to the Form of Making and Ordaining Prieſts and Deacons in the Church of</hi> England. <hi>And that every Perſon Ordained only by Presbyters, ſince the Year of our Lord</hi> 1660. <hi>ſhall not be admitted to any Benefice, unleſs he receive a Second Impoſition of Hands from ſome Biſhop, to recommend him to the Grace of God, for the Work or Exerciſe of his Office, in the Place or Charge unto which he is Called; and the Biſhop ſhall frame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Words accordingly.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59203:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
AND WHEREAS, <hi>by a Statute made in the</hi> 13th. <hi>and</hi> 14th. <hi>Year of his Late Majeſty's Reign, Entituled,</hi> An Act for the Uniformity of the Publick Prayer, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Rites and Ceremonies; and for Eſtabliſhing the Form of Ordaining and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, in the Church of <hi>England, there are Two Declarations impoſed upon ſeveral Perſons, and in ſuch manner as is there Specified:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>BE IT FURTHER ENACTED, <hi>by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Perſon, that ſhall hereafter be preſented, or collated, or put into any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Benefice, or Promotion, ſhall declare his unfeigned Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Uſe of all things contained, and preſcribed in the Book of</hi> Common-Prayer; <hi>nor make and ſubſcribe the other Declaration or Acknowledgment,</hi> viz. (I. A. B. Do declare, That it is not Lawful to take up Arms againſt the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                           <hi>&amp;c.) according to the Forms in the ſaid Act, in the</hi> 13th. <hi>and</hi> 14th. <hi>Year of his Majeſties Reign, directed and appointed: But that both the ſaid Declarations ſhall be wholly omitted; any thing in the aforeſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute to the contrary, notwithſtanding.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AND <hi>be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall hereafter be capable of being collated, admitted, or put into any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Benefice, or Promotion, before ſuch time as the ſaid Perſon ſhall have taken the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance before the Biſhop of the Dioceſs (who is hereby impowred to adminiſter the ſame) and ſhall alſo make and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Declaration, mentioned in an Act of Parliament, made in the</hi> 30th. <hi>Year of the Reign of King</hi> Charles <hi>the</hi> II. <hi>Entituled,</hi> An Act to prevent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts from Sitting in either Houſe of Parliament: <hi>And the Name of every Perſon, ſo taking the Oath, and making and ſubſcribing the Declaration afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall be enrolled, with the Day and Time of his taking the ſame, in Rolls to be kept by the reſpective Biſhops of each Dioceſs, for that purpoſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AND <hi>be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Perſon ſhall hereafter be obliged to take the Oath of Canonical Obedience, or to make the Subſcription required by the Canons, or to go to the Biſhops for a Licenſe to Preach, being already Lawfully Ordained; any Statute or Cuſtom to the contrary, notwithſtanding.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AND <hi>be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforeſaid, That from henceforth, no Perſon wear a Surplice, during the Time of Reading Common Prayer, or Preaching, or performing any Religious Worſhip, in any Church or Chappel whatſoever; except only in the Chappel of the Kings Majesty, and all Cathedral Churches of this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and Dominion of</hi> Wales.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59203:5"/>
AND <hi>be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforeſaid, That from henceforth no Miniſter, or other Eccleſiaſtical Perſon, ſhall be obliged or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to uſe the Sign of the Croſs in Baptiſm; or any Parent obliged to have his Child Chriſtened by the Miniſter of the Pariſh, if the ſaid Miniſter will not uſe, or omit the Sign of the Croſs, according to the deſire of the Parents; who in that Caſe may procure ſome other Miniſter to do it. Nor ſhall the Child of any Perſon be refuſed Baptiſm, for want of any God-fathers, and God-mothers, ſo long as the Parent is preſent to fill their place.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AND <hi>be it further Enacted, by the Authority aforeſaid, That no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or Eccleſiaſtical Perſon, that ſhall officiate in the Adminiſtration of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, ſhall refuſe it to any perſon, that deſires to be admitted to the ſame, although ſuch perſon ſhall not uſe the geſture of Kneeling in the Act of receiving, nor come up to the Comunion-Table; but ſhall go to ſuch convenient place of the Church, where ſuch Perſon is; and there give it him in ſome other decent gesture, of Ordinary uſe in the Reformed Churches. Nor ſhall any Miniſter be troubled for the with-holding his own Act, in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Sacrament, from any whom he judges Notoriouſly Unworthy, or unfit for it: Nor for Suſpending his Reading the Sentence of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, againſt any of his Pariſh, untill he be ſatisfied in the Caſe, that his Crime deſerves it.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And to the intent, that Uniformity may (ſo far as it is needful, and ſo far as it can) be ſtill Maintained, be it Enacted moreover, by the Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, That every Parſon, Vicar, and Lecturer, ſhall conform to the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the Church, in the Ordinary Lords-day Service, Reading the ſame by himſelf, or Aſſiſtant, as by Law it is Eſtabliſhed: Reſerving a Neceſſary, and Juſt Liberty for his</hi> Conſcience, <hi>in any Matter or Words, which himſelf eſteems unlawful (and ſo to him it is Sin) and alſo for</hi> Prudence, <hi>in the whole management, to Act with reſpect to Time, Place and Circumſtances ſo as appears moſt conducive to Edification. And as long as the main Body of the Service appointed, is there Read, and the ſubſtance of the Offices be there Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, he ſhall not be Puniſhable for any breach otherwiſe of the Acts of Uniformity; any thing in the ſaid Statutes to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AND <hi>for as much as there are ſome Ministers ef a good Life, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (according to their Judgments) allow of our Parochial Churches, nor the Book of Liturgy; but do chooſe to Worſhip God, and Jeſus Chriſt, in the way of their Gathered, and Separate Congregations; and crave the Protection, and Clemency of the King, upon their Allegiance as other Subjects:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>BE <hi>it Enacted furthermore, by the Authority aforeſaid, That for the Happineſs, and quiet of the Realm, and the Reduction of theſe Men, by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                           <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59203:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                           <hi>means, than thoſe that have hitherto proved Unſucceſsful, All Proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Penal Laws, againſt the Nonconformiſts, of every ſort that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Proteſtant Religion, be ſuſpended, untill, by a further Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thoſe that are fit to be</hi> Tolerated, <hi>and the</hi> Intolerable <hi>ſhall be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; and ſuch Order be taken as is neceſſary, to the Settling a firm and laſting Union in the Nation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Thus much for the Firſt, and Second thing, the <hi>Deſign</hi> and <hi>Bill;</hi> now for the Third, ſome little <hi>Animadverſions</hi> upon it. I muſt confeſs my ſelf One, that am concerned, and that have been ſo ſtill, when <hi>Parliaments</hi> Sate, both in my Mind, and my Endeavours to the utmoſt, for Peace and Union in the Church; which is the cauſe that this <hi>Bill,</hi> thus produced, was put and left upon Record, on purpoſe in that Book mentioned, for ſome future <hi>Parliament</hi> to uſe it ſelf, or to take <hi>Meaſure by,</hi> for making <hi>another,</hi> if they would fit the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Caſe, and accompliſh the End deſign'd. And now am I afraid at my Heart, leſt when we have ſuch an opportunity, as we never had really before, when <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the whole <hi>People</hi> are for Uniting the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as our Intereſt, againſt the danger of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> from abroad, and at home, there ſhould be ſome Obſtruction yet put to this Accommodation, which is ſo forward and hopeful; either through the Machinations of ſome <hi>cloſe Enemies,</hi> by ſuch Methods as we cannot <hi>diſcern,</hi> and ſo cannot <hi>prevent;</hi> or through the ſhortneſs of <hi>true Friends,</hi> who for want of knowing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly what it is the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> muſt have, may be over-ſeen, or over-reacht, and ſit down with ſomething leſs than will ſerve the turn; and for that Reaſon have I gathered together, and do put forth this Paper, though not without much Reluctancy; becauſe I know well, that ſome men will be ready to ſay, Who are you? and what have you to do with theſe Matters, which belong to the Parliament? But I ſay, They do belong to me, and are the Concern of every Body; and if, for lack of a little intimation at firſt, the Nonconformiſt ſhould come to have their Conſciences choakt, and be deprived of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty at laſt, thoſe Men of all other, that now would ſtave me back, and reprove me for medling, might more deſervedly be the Firſt to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid us all, and ſay, Why did you not look better to it, when it was Time? You may thank your ſelves; it was through your own negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that you had not what you would, at ſuch a Seaſon.</p>
            <p>Be it known therefore, (or remembred) that there being two <hi>Bills</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi> upon the <hi>Anvil,</hi> in <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59203:6"/>
the One of them for <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> the Other for <hi>Indulgence;</hi> (the Titles were otherwiſe worded, but the Intent ſuch): The Bill for <hi>Indulgence</hi> was ſo well attended by an induſtrious Member of the Houſe, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was wanting to the Compleating of it; but the Bill for <hi>Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> being drawn up by Gentlemen that did not, and could not fully underſtand the Scruples of the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> was both imperfect and neglected: Only one Perſon, without door, having procured a Copy, and finding it ſo; did by applying himſelf to ſeveral Members about it, get ſomething to be changed, or put into it, at the <hi>Committee;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (with Conſent, and Aſſiſtance of ſome of his Brethren) <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> it, againſt the <hi>Sitting</hi> of the Parliament at <hi>Oxford;</hi> but they ſitting not, it was thought good to put it as a Memorial into that Book, and for that end, as is mentioned.</p>
            <p>When I ſay, now, this <hi>Bill</hi> was <hi>perfected;</hi> as I mean it only in regard to the <hi>Contents,</hi> leaving the <hi>Words</hi> to be formed better, as a <hi>Parliament</hi> pleaſed; ſo by this <hi>Perfection,</hi> I mean not ſuch a <hi>Meaſure,</hi> as all thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcentions, or Allowances, ſit to to be made to the Diſſenter, may not <hi>Exceed</hi> (for there is the <hi>Service-Book</hi> may be Reviſed, and every thing in it, that gives occaſion of ſtumbling to any, may be changed, and there are other things may be expected at this time, which could not rationally heretofore)<hi>:</hi> but ſuch a <hi>Meaſure,</hi> as they muſt not fall <hi>ſhort of,</hi> without rendring the Bill inſignificant. For if there be ten Thorns in the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> Foot, and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> pull out <hi>Nine</hi> of them, and leave the <hi>Tenth,</hi> he cannot go along with them for that <hi>One</hi> only. There are ſome few <hi>Additions</hi> therefore inſerted in this <hi>Bill,</hi> which were not put into it by the <hi>Committee</hi> at that time; the Reaſons where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will appear in their own Light; Excepting Two of them, which I will therefore ſpeak ſomething about, the One being concerning the Subſcription of the <hi>Articles,</hi> the Other concerning <hi>Orders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will begin with that concerning <hi>Orders.</hi> In the late Times, when the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were down, many were Ordained by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> was willing to allow thoſe <hi>Orders,</hi> as good in a Caſe of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: But there being Others ordained ſince the return of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, there was no Proviſion made for ſuch in the <hi>Bill.</hi> As for theſe Perſons therefore, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e neglect of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> may be countenanced, here is the Propoſal of ſuch a <hi>Laying on of their Hands,</hi> which may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully received. For there is <hi>Ordinatio ad Oſſicium, &amp; Reordinatio ad Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritium particulare</hi> may conſiſt together. An Ordination to the <hi>Office,</hi> or <hi>Miniſtry</hi> it ſelf, is not to be repeated. He that is once ordained to That, whether by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops,</hi> cannot receive the Spiritual Power
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59203:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(or Character,) or be made Miniſters, <hi>Again:</hi> But there is a <hi>Laying on of Hands</hi> to the <hi>Work</hi> of that Office, in regard to a new <hi>Charge,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who were Miniſters before, are yet <hi>ſeparated</hi> to that <hi>peculiar Work,</hi> unto which the Holy Ghoſt called them <hi>(Acts</hi> 13.) By the <hi>Laying on of the Hands</hi> of thoſe at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and ſuch an Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as this, being capable to be uſed more than once, is the Remedy applyed therefore to theſe Perſons in the <hi>Bill,</hi> as the only <hi>medium</hi> for Reſolution of this Difficulty.</p>
            <p>For the Other matter concerning the Subſcription to the Churches Articles, I have ſomething more than this, to ſay about it. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever have read a Book, called, <hi>A part of Regiſter,</hi> wherein there is a relation of ſeveral things, in reference to the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Days, they will find, that nothing was then ſo grievous to them, as the <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> of thoſe Times, and the Subſcription to theſe <hi>Articles</hi> was one; which gives me Affliction to conſider, how by the Contexture of both thoſe Bills, before named, and like now, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and be two again, the Nonconformiſt Miniſters whole Freedom from Proſecution of the Law againſt him, is made to depend upon his Subſcribing the <hi>Articles of Religion;</hi> A bottom I muſt ſay, more narrow, more ſervile, and leſs ingenuous, than might be wiſhed. For what man of a free Judgment can Subſcribe to the 39. or 36. Articles, which himſelf hath not drawn up, without a Liberty of his own interpretation? Indeed, if that were a thing lawful, upon the reading the Articles, to frame a Senſe of ones own, and Subſcribe it in that ſenſe; nothing would be more eaſie, than ſuch a Subſcription: But when the <hi>Impoſitions</hi> of our <hi>Superiours</hi> muſt conſcientiouſly be taken in the Senſe of the <hi>Impoſers,</hi> or elſe we do but prevaricate, are falſe, or perjurious in the ſight of God: there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing almoſt under Heaven, that a Man ſhould be more tender of, than this buſineſs of <hi>Subſcribing.</hi> The doubtfulneſs of many about the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> is not to be compared to a Conviction of Conſcience that a Man muſt not Subſcribe to any point of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves untrue; and I muſt needs add, that Except <hi>the Declaring and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that it is not lawful to take Arms againſt thoſe that are Commiſſionated by the King, upon any cauſe,</hi> there is no part of <hi>Conformity</hi> more hard to my Genius, than this <hi>Subſcription.</hi> It is an unfortunate thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that, when Aſſent and Conſent to the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> is found a thing ſo truly grievous to all, as to be judg'd neceſſary to be taken away; this Aſſent and Conſent yet, and Approbation of the Articles, ſhould be thought no Grievance to any Body. Eſpecially, when in <hi>One,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59203:7"/>
the Conformiſt hath a Shift, or Salvo, that he Subſcribes but to the <hi>Uſe:</hi> but in the <hi>Other,</hi> there is no Shift, no Salvo at all, nothing but down-right Hypocriſie and Falſe-hood; when a Man comes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes his Aſſent and Conſent to, and Approbation of, thoſe Articles in the <hi>Churches</hi> Senſe, but does underſtand them to be true, only in his <hi>own.</hi> I know indeed, that in the Opinion of many, ſome of our more eminent Divines, the Subſcribing the Articles is to be taken for nothing but a Reſpect to the Church, and an Engagement, that they will not Preach againſt them: But theſe Men, how worthy, or how conſcientious they be otherwiſe, muſt be told, that in this they ſhew no Conſcience; for I would know from any ſuch Man, in what <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionary</hi> I ſhall find, that <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to an <hi>Article</hi> and <hi>Approbation</hi> of it, is no more than I won't <hi>Preach</hi> againſt it. And what Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after that ſhall hold him, who can get leave of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to make ſuch an Evaſion? Beſides that, to promiſe I will never Preach or Write againſt theſe <hi>Articles,</hi> if I believe the Church miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Doctrine of any of them, is really to me a harder Task, than to Subſcribe them; in as much as to tell <hi>one</hi> Lye, is not ſo grievous as to tell a great <hi>many;</hi> which as often as I break my Promiſe, I muſt be doing.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion therefore here ariſes upon this, What the Parliament ſhould do about this Subſcription, ſeeing it is a Grievance undoubtedly, and ought to be Redreſſed? Now there are Four ways may be propoſed; Either the removing it, or changing it, or providing a Salve againſt it; or that, which is leaſt, letting this little <hi>Addition</hi> ſtand, and be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed That which is put into the Bill, for that end.</p>
            <p>For the firſt Way, I muſt needs ſay, That <hi>that</hi> is the eaſieſt; and it is a common Saying, <hi>The firſt is beſt.</hi> And what does hinder, but this <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to the <hi>Articles</hi> may be taken away, as well as <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to the Book of Common Prayer? Here are the ſame crooked<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs's to ſtick in our Throats, and why ſhould not both De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations fare alike? Why, is it not enoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Man to profeſs his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Scripture, and of the Apoſtles Creed, and to take the Teſt againſt Popery, to qualify him for the benefit of any Bill of this kind?</p>
            <p>For the Second Way, which I ſuppoſe to be the moſt likely to take Effect, is this. Let theſe Declarations of our <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to, and Approbation of the Articles, which we are required now to Subſcribe, be turned into a Declaration of That which the more inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous of our Conformiſts do ſay, is all their meaning in their Subſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them; and that Expedient may do the buſineſs. We muſt not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59203:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Subſcribe to ſuch Words as theſe, with the Reſervation of a leſs Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That is Equivocation; but we may Subſcribe to ſuch Words as ſignifie only that Meaning, inſtead of theſe which ſignifie more, and be at eaſe in our <hi>Subſcription.</hi> I <hi>A. B. do declare,</hi> That I do bear that due Reſpect to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and her Book of <hi>Articles,</hi> as an Inſtrument of Concord; That I will not <hi>Seditiouſly</hi> or <hi>Schiſmatically,</hi> I will not <hi>directly</hi> or <hi>expreſly</hi> Preach or Write againſt any of them, to the Breach of Charity, or making diſturbance among Chriſtians. There are ſome ſuch Words as theſe muſt be put in, for <hi>conſequentially</hi> and <hi>reductively,</hi> or before we are aware <hi>innocently,</hi> and ſometime <hi>neceſſarily,</hi> in regard to ſome point of Doctrine, which we think in their Senſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Scripture; we muſt and ſhall Preach againſt them, and yet our Promiſe muſt not be broken. I will, to avoid Scruple, quite as to my ſelf, and for the fuller ſatisfaction to my Conformiſt Brethren, and to acquit my Conſcience before all ſorts of Men, make this Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my own Accord. That <hi>I do from my Heart give my Conſent to the Reformation of Religion, which was made by the Church of</hi> England <hi>in her Doctrine, and her Worſhip: I do eſteem thoſe Perſons, that are made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters by her Book of Orders, to be lawful Miniſters, and our Parochial Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be true Chriſtian Churches, conſiſting of Paſture and People, who have a Fundamental Authority from Chriſt, of Teaching and Ruling them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Inſtitution; I do ſubmit to her Government, as under the King: And I do receive her Articles and Homilies, as Books full of wholeſom Truth, and good Inſtructions, Inſtrumental to Concord; and that They contain in them all things neceſſary to Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Third Way, It is that, which, if I might chooſe, I ſhould prefer before any, as moſt agreeable to my Spirit (for the ſake of other Incumbrances like this): and my Propoſal ſhall be the putting into the Bill (or ſuch Bills) a Clauſe for the ſaving a Mans Conſcience, though he do Subſcribe, and ſubmit to ſuch Injunctions as theſe are; and that Clauſe which I would offer upon this account, ſhould be to this <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> committing the <hi>Words</hi> (here and before) if they offend, to the amendment of the Lawyers.<hi>—And foraſmuch as all Impoſitions are to be taken in the Senſe of the Impoſers, unleſs ſome proviſion of Liberty, Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or Exception be made for the Taker to do otherwiſe, it is hereby declared, That this Subſcription (Aſſent, Conſent, Approbation) is not impoſed, or to be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on any in the very Senſe and Meaning of the Compilers of the Articles or Impoſers (whereof a Man can never be ſure, and hardly ſo much perſwaded of ſometimes, as to act in Faith) but in a Rational Conſtruction (agreeable to the Holy Scripture) of the Subſcribers own, or of ſome judicious Expoſitor;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59203:8"/>
               <hi>that is, in the Terms of the School, not in the Authentick, but a Doctrinal Interpretation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Fourth and Laſt Way, which is That I take in this Bill, in regard to the Paſſing it with the leſs Notice (for it is brought-in, as the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> may ſee, in a Parentheſis); I muſt confeſs it to be ſome thing co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident with the third, but more confined; conſiſting in a Liberty of a Man's own Senſe, for ſuch as ſcruple at any Article, but ſo as to bring his <hi>Explication</hi> to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that if it be <hi>Heretical,</hi> he may reject him; if <hi>Orthodox,</hi> receive him: and ſo a due Regard be had to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of ſuch Perſons, and yet the Church not neglected upon that Account.</p>
            <p>By this way of Providing againſt the Scruples of the more Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, about this momentous piece of Conformity, the Subſcription to the Articles, (when the Proviſion only of the Exception of Three of them will be too ſhort) we muſt not underſtand this Bill to be drawn up ſo, becauſe this way is beſt; but upon Suppoſition, that neither of the other Propoſals would be granted, and alſo, becauſe this Bill is no <hi>new</hi> Bill now, but <hi>Produced:</hi> This is a Bill Printed Six or Seven Years ſince; and at that time, this way was that only which could be thought on (and in this manner to be brought in) as more likely to be Paſſed.</p>
            <p>Howbeit, the Scene now being altered, I cannot tell but one of the other ways may paſs ſooner; and this I am ſure, that ſome Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion herein, appears more and more neceſſary from that Conſideration which is yet farther to be preſſed, the difficulty (I mean) at bottom, which lies here. The <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> muſt be taken in the Senſe of the <hi>Church.</hi> The Parliament indeed impoſes the Subſcription; but is not the Impoſer in whoſe Senſe the Articles muſt be taken, becauſe it enjoyns them as the <hi>Churches Articles,</hi> that is all one as enjoyning them to be taken in her Senſe; and that Church is the Church in Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Days, when the <hi>Articles</hi> were compiled and enjoined at firſt. And hereupon, I will offer one Inſtance; and ſuppoſe a Man to ſcruple the <hi>11th.</hi> Article, which tells us, That we are <hi>juſtified</hi> by <hi>Faith only.</hi> I do here believe in my Conſcience, that the Senſe wherein the Church then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood This, muſt be the Senſe of our Firſt Reformers, and that is by <hi>Faith</hi> taken Objective, <hi>in ſenſu Correlativo,</hi> not as a <hi>Work,</hi> but an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument;</hi> which in ſhort is, in ſuch a Senſe (which Divines know) as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all Works, <hi>Evangelical</hi> as well as <hi>Legal,</hi> from Juſtification. I will ſuppoſe now, that the Man comes to the Biſhop, and ſays, He can not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe this Article in the Churches Senſe, becauſe he verily believes this to be her Senſe; and that to be inconſiſtent with St. <hi>James,</hi> who ſays direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59203:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the contrary, That <hi>by Works a Man is Juſtified, and not by Faith only:</hi> and therefore deſires he may ſubſcribe in his own Senſe, which he is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to tender, <hi>viz.</hi> That by <hi>Faith</hi> he underſtands Chriſtianity, or the <hi>becoming a Chriſtian;</hi> and that by <hi>Faith only,</hi> he underſtands St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Faith without Works,</hi> that is, Faith without the Works of the <hi>Law,</hi> or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> and living according to the <hi>Laws;</hi> and ſo he gives in the Senſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for the Senſe of the <hi>Article;</hi> That a Man is not juſtified by living according to the <hi>Law,</hi> but living according to the <hi>Goſpel only.</hi> I would ask now, Whether there be not reaſon here, both that ſuch a Man ſhould not be excluded for this ſcruple; and that there ſhould be Licenſe provided by ſome ſuch Clauſe in the Bill, for the Biſhops to admit him upon this Explanation; Eſpecially, ſeeing the Reconciliation of St. <hi>James</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is thereby made ſo clear, as it muſt tempt his Acceptation.</p>
            <p>As for the Roman Catholicks at laſt, I will not baulk my Opinion. The <hi>King</hi> (while Prince of <hi>Orange)</hi> hath expreſly ſaid in his Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he <hi>Excepts not the Papiſts,</hi> And I need not refrain my conſtant Thoughts. I am one my ſelf, be ſure, that am not for <hi>Popery,</hi> but muſt diſtinguiſh between the danger of it when it is in <hi>Dominion,</hi> (that is Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt by Law or Force) and where it is in <hi>Subjugation:</hi> I very much dread the <hi>One,</hi> I am very gentle toward the <hi>Other.</hi> In order to this, I muſt be againſt the Permiſſion of Factors for a Foreign Juriſdiction; yet ſhould not murmur, if the Sanguinary Laws (whereby ſuch a Crime is made, as Treaſon, to be capital) were repealed. Again, I am one not for the <hi>Maſs,</hi> and a general open tolerating its <hi>Votaries</hi> in the <hi>Publick Aſſemblies;</hi> becauſe all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> judg it <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and that open <hi>Idolatry</hi> is not to be tolerated, where it can be helped: But for the private pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable <hi>Recuſant,</hi> that enjoys his Religion to himſelf, and meddles not with other Folks, his Caſe is the ſame (I judg) with the <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> and I am ſtill for our doing to them, as we would have had them do unto us but a while ago, ſin only excepted. <hi>Yet not altogether with the Idolater, for then muſt ye needs go out of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have no more to ſay now, but ſome little about the turning the <hi>Two</hi> Bills (as they were formerly in the Houſe) into <hi>One,</hi> which is done by the Print from whence I took it; the Reaſon whereof, I ſuppoſe, was the tediouſneſs of the <hi>Bill</hi> for <hi>Indulgence;</hi> which providing for the Caſe of ſo many, and ſomething or other being like to be omitted, it ſeemed more eaſie, and more ſafe, to wrap up all theſe Caſes together, in the ſecurity of a general Suſpenſion of the Penal Laws about Religion, until a Parliament come that can have leiſure, by a <hi>Committee</hi> or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59203:9"/>
of Two or Three Sedulous <hi>Lawyers,</hi> that are fit for the Work, and willing to attend it, to look over all the Statutes that concern <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> for the finding out every thing that is hard, and fit to be Repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, whether it be the whole <hi>Act,</hi> (or the <hi>Act</hi> at <hi>Oxford)</hi> or part of it (as the Uniformity <hi>Act)</hi> to the end, that thoſe Parts and Clauſes (if over grievous but to the Papiſts themſelves) being duly conſidered, and Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thoroughly adjuſted, an <hi>Act</hi> may be drawn up, that ſhould be a Repealing <hi>Act,</hi> to deliver us from ſuch Burdens altogether; and that were the moſt Effectual <hi>Indulgence,</hi> or beſt way to it, that is imaginable: And as for <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> then, which is a matter of more Curioſity, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and Counſel, It were well that this <hi>Bill</hi> here propoſed, might be brought in, and paſt for a <hi>Staying Act,</hi> or <hi>Interim</hi> of <hi>Pacification,</hi> until a Tryal of the Comprehended; ſome Conſults of the Comprehended and Indulged; a Convocation of the Conformiſts, with part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended choſen into that Convocation; a Reviſal of the Churches Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, their Book of Orders, their Articles, their Homilies, their Canons, with other ſuch preliminary matters pre-ordered, may Adminiſter the Advantage to a more compleat <hi>Act,</hi> and better Eſtabliſhment, than can be expected at this Seaſon. I will conclude with what is apt at preſent; <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> without <hi>Indulgence</hi> deſtroys the Separatiſt, that is both the Papiſts and Sectaries. <hi>Indulgence</hi> without <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> depopulates the Church. <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> with <hi>Indulgence</hi> Unites the Proteſtants, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and gives Eaſe and Safety to all People.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALthough there was ſo much Care taken of the</hi> Bill of Indulgence <hi>(as I have ſaid</hi> Page 10.) <hi>when drawn up, that nothing needful ſhould be left out; yet am I told very newly, That there is one Clauſe in the</hi> Act of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity, <hi>making</hi> Diſſenters <hi>lyable to pay</hi> 100 l. <hi>for adminiſtring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, eſcaped their Remembrance; and that it is good therefore ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Words, providing a Covering for them from all Danger, by</hi> Common <hi>and</hi> Statute Law unknown, <hi>as well as from the Penalties of the</hi> Law enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merated, <hi>were added to the Bill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59203:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>BEfore I ſent the fore-going Sheets to the <hi>Preſs,</hi> I underſtood that the Bill for <hi>Indulgence</hi> was brought into the <hi>Houſe of Lords;</hi> and knowing the Contexture long ſince, it made me ſpeak ſo much of the Subſcription to the Articles, as I have done. Since then I have ſeen the Bill for <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> which is brought in There likewiſe. And though I cannot but in Gratitude take notice of the Candour in it, that the Subſcription to the Articles is waved there; yet do I find Two things in it, which the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> will ſtick at, ſo that if they be not mended, the Bill is like to do no Good.</p>
            <p>One of theſe things like to ſtick, is this Declaration: <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Doctrine, Worſhip, and Government of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as by Law Eſtabliſhed,</hi> &amp;c. The Government here intended, includes the Hierarchy, with its Officers and Offices, Lay-Chancellours, Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als—, and I know not what more we muſt Subſcribe to, when we ſay, we <hi>approve of this Government.</hi> And when the <hi>36th.</hi> Article of the Church is excepted from our Subſcription in the <hi>Bill of Indulgence,</hi> as known to have been ſo grievous to the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> from Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s days untill now, in regard to the <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> though it ſays only, that the Book for their Conſecration <hi>hath in it nothing Superſtitious and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly</hi> (which it may not have, though in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing otherwiſe we may not <hi>approve</hi> it,) I wonder it ſhould not come to be thought, that ſuch words would not down with our <hi>Nonconformiſts, I approve of this Government;</hi> Eſpecially when ſome of the moſt Grave of them, have took the <hi>Covenant</hi> for its Extirpation. I ſhall therefore humbly beſeech the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> if it be not too late, or if it be, the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> that if ſuch a Declaration muſt be impoſed, ſome ſuch words as theſe may be ſubſtituted in its room: <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do heartily approve of the Reformation made by the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in her Doctrine</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59203:10"/>
               <hi>and Worſhip: I ſhall ſubmit to her Government, ſo far as I can with a good Conſcience: And I receive her Articles, as conducive to Concord, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining in them all things neceſſary to Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Other Thing like to ſtick, is the Buſineſs of <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to thoſe that have been ordained only by <hi>Presbyters;</hi> and it is to be noted, that there is a <hi>Device</hi> offered in this Bill, for Reconciling the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> by giving Satisfaction to Both<hi>:</hi> The Biſhop challenges a ſole Right of giving Orders, from the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> (as they are called) and from <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> (even <hi>Jerom</hi> himſelf) down to the Reformation: And the Miniſters ordained by Presbyters plead the Cuſtom of the Reformed Churches, and their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from Chriſt; accounting, that the Spiritual Power comes not by the Hands which are laid on him, whether of Biſhop or Presbyter, (and therefore ſays <hi>Hooker, We breath not on the Ordained, as Chriſt did)</hi> but flows immediately (the Conditions being put) from Chriſt's Inſtitution. If the Biſhop part with this Privilege, he degrades himſelf of the Power the Church hath given him; and if the Miniſter recedes from his former Orders, he departs from the Authority Chriſt hath given him. To reconcile both, this is the <hi>Device.</hi> The Biſhop ſhall acknowledg the Perſon ordained by Presbyters, to be a Miniſter alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whoſe Miniſterial Acts have been and are valid, as the Acts of any other Miniſter; and that he ordains him not therefore to the <hi>Office,</hi> which he has already, but admits him to the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of his Miniſtry in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and conſequently to the Emoluments that may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to him upon that Account. The Man was, and is, and muſt be a <hi>Miniſter of Chriſt</hi> before; but he is no <hi>Legal</hi> Miniſter, or not to be <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, reputed, held</hi> to all Intents and Purpoſes a <hi>Miniſter of the Church of England,</hi> till he hath received Impoſition of Hands from a Biſhop. He is a Miniſter before, <hi>in foro Dei,</hi> but not till then a Miniſter <hi>in foro Eccleſiae Anglicanae.</hi> As a Man, who is a <hi>Graduate,</hi> or made <hi>Doctor</hi> beyond Sea, and comes to <hi>London;</hi> he is, and muſt be acknowledged a true <hi>Doctor;</hi> but he ſhall not have Liberty to <hi>Practiſe,</hi> till admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our College of Phyſitians.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs my ſelf partial in my reſpect to this <hi>Device;</hi> for I ſuppoſe it deriv'd from Dr. <hi>Wilkins</hi>'s credit into this Bill; and I know from whence, and upon what account, he received it. I will therefore ſay thus much for it; That if this <hi>Device,</hi> may be owned, and acknowledged for what it is, that is, a <hi>New Thing,</hi> or a <hi>New Inſtitution</hi> in the Church, for which an Office ſhould be made, and no trick put on the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> by it: As I ſee no cauſe then, why ſuch an Eccleſiaſtical Inſtitution,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59203:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
being neceſſary for Peace-ſake, might not be <hi>Made;</hi> ſo do I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend no unlawfulneſs in the ſubmitting to it. If any ill be in it, it muſt lie on the part of the Biſhop, who brings in a Thing into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, which I confeſs I never read of in Antiquity, and which I believe is not to be found in Chriſtendom; For a Miniſter of <hi>England</hi> is not Re-ordained by the <hi>French,</hi> or by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to make him a Miniſter of the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> Church, though it might be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe here, becauſe the Reaſon for it before mentioned, is not there as here<hi>:</hi> But as to the part of the <hi>Submitter,</hi> the evil of Re-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination lying only in the Vacating our firſt Miniſtry, which is Sacriledge, and here being no ſuch matter, ſo long as our former Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is publickly profeſſed by the man himſelf, and Biſhop, and whole Church, there can be no Evil (I ſay) in a ſecond Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Hands, as thus uſed only, unleſs you will ſay, it is a breach of the Third Commandment, a taking an Ordinance of God in Vain; when there is here no <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> at all, but an <hi>Humane Inſtitution</hi> for ſo good an end as Peace in the Church; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made the Qualification of a perſon, for the uſe of his Miniſtry in publick, and the enjoyment of a <hi>Living,</hi> Who is the man that will ſay, it is done in vain? Nevertheleſs, if this <hi>Device</hi> ſhould happily paſs Both Houſes (which being a <hi>New Thing,</hi> and preſented bare faced, will rather be called a <hi>Monſter,</hi> and turn'd out of Doors) two things muſt be adviſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One</hi> is, That in the adminiſtring ſuch an Inſtitution, Inſtead of theſe words, the Biſhop is appointed to uſe, <hi>Take thou Authority to Exerciſe thy Miniſtry in the Church of</hi> England (whereat the Nonconformiſt Miniſter having his Miniſterial Authority already, will Scruple) it is better theſe be uſed: <hi>Receive thou Admittance, by the Impoſition of my Hands, to the Exerciſe of thy Miniſtry, in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and in any Church in my Dioceſs where thou ſhall be called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Other</hi> is, That the adminiſtrating ſuch an humane Ordinance as this, in order to Union, may not be called <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> which is a Name ſo odious in the Church in all Ages; but as it is a <hi>New Thing,</hi> and ought to have a <hi>New Office</hi> appointed for it; ſo it ſhould have a <hi>New Name</hi> alſo. Let a Conſtitution or <hi>Canon</hi> be made for it, and an <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Form</hi> to adminiſter it, and let it be called <hi>Cannonical Admiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have ſaid thus much, This is not the thing wherein I am concern'd in my <hi>Bill.</hi> To be ordained to the Office of a Miniſter, does make a Man, in common account, a Miniſter of the <hi>Univerſal Church;</hi> and a Miniſter of the <hi>Church Univerſal,</hi> muſt be a Miniſter in her
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59203:11"/>
Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>Holland,</hi> and of every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and the Impoſition of Hands, to make a Man a Miniſter in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who was a Miniſter in every one before, is a <hi>New Thing,</hi> (I have ſaid) and perhaps will be thought an <hi>Odd Thing</hi> too: But to make a Man, who is a Miniſter already of the Univerſal Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be the Miniſter of ſuch a <hi>particular</hi> place, that was not their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Miniſter before, is no <hi>New Thing,</hi> nor <hi>Odd Thing.</hi> And if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon, not Epiſcopally ordained already, ſhall be bound to go to his Biſhop, when he has ſuch a Call, for his Bleſſing, with Impoſition of Hands in reference to ſuch a Place, that is, to pray for God's Bleſſing or Aſſiſtance of him, to fulfill that Work; there can be nothing of Scruple or doubt about the Lawfulneſs of his ſo doing. Only I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an Office here to be made, as I have ſaid before, and in a Prayer fitted to the Caſe, the Perſon being on his knees, and the Biſhop read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over him, I would inſtead of thoſe words before preſcribed, have theſe only brought in,<hi>—Whom by this Impoſition of my Hands, we recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the Grace of God, for the Work unto which he is called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing yet I muſt take notice of, That in the Bill for <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> in <hi>Charles</hi>'s time, it came to be allowed at the <hi>Committee,</hi> that the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of thoſe that were ordained only by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> from 1644. to 1660. ſhould be held good (though Others were left to be Re-ordained); and I cannot but be Sorry, that a thing ſo ſmall, ſo equitable as that (when there was no Biſhops to go to for Orders) ſhould be with drawn; Seeing the Teſtimony of an <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> to the Validity of <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Orders,</hi> in honour to the Reformed Churches abroad, were ſome conſiderable Attainment.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
